Register of the Joseph Hansen Papers, 1887-1980.
Hoover Institution Archives
- EDITORIAL FILE, 1924-1979.
  - Fourth International. United Secretariat
    - "Draft Resolution on Latin America," 1968. Includes Livio Maitan, "An Insufficient Document," 1968. Mimeograph (from Socialist Workers Party International Information Bulletin [1969 January]) with handwritten annotations (Folder 32)
    - "The Algerian Revolution from 1962 to 1969, " 1969 (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - "Preliminary Draft Theses for the World Congress: The World Revolution in the 1970s, " 1969 (Folder 2)
    - "The Worldwide Youth Radicalization and the Tasks of the Fourth International," 1969 (Folder 3)
    - "The Building of Revolutionary Parties in Capitalist Europe," 1972. Printed copy (from Socialist Workers Party International Internal Discussion Bulletin [1972 November]) with handwritten annotations (Folder 4)
    - Draft program, 1972 (drafts in French by Pierre Frank and Ernest Mandel) (Folder 5-6)
    - "Draft Resolution on Portugal," 1975 (Folder 7)
    - "Draft Statement on Vietnam," 1975 (Folder 8)
    - "Summary of Draft Theses on the World Situation since 1968, " 1977 (Folder 9)
    - "Draft Resolution on Socialist Democracy and Multi-Party System under the Dictatorship of the Proletariat," ca. 1978 (Folder 10)
  - Fraccion Bolchevique Leninista (Liga Socialista [Mexico]), "Fact Sheet on the Internal Struggle in the Liga Socialista," 1976 (Folder 11)
  - Frank, Pierre
    - " August 1953, " 1953 (Folder 12)
    - "France," ca. 1964 (Folder 13)
    - "Constructing an International...with Quotations," 1965 (Folder 14)
    - Une Revision du Trotskysme: A Propos de la Rupture de Pablo avec la IVe Internationale, 1966 (English translation) (Folder 15)
    - "Report to United Secretariat Meeting on Meetings with Healy," 1970 (Folder 16)
  - Frank, Pierre, Livio Maitan, and Ernest Mandel, "In Defense of the Portuguese Revolution," 1975. Printed copy (from Intercontinental Press [1975 September 8]) with handwritten annotations) (Folder 17)
  - Gabriel, C., statement on Angola, 1975 (Folder 18)
  - Garrett, Jan
    - "Portrait of a Paid Killer," 1967 (Folder 19)
    - Review of Regis Debray, Revolution in the Revolution? Armed Struggle and Political Struggle in Latin America, 1967 (Folder 20)
  - Genecin, Milton
    - " IP Correction," 1972 (Folder 21)
    - "A Criticism of the Draft Political Resolution," 1973 (Folder 22)
  - "Germany," 1963 (Folder 23)
  - Gordon, Sam, "Healy's Smear against Trotsky's Last Collaborators," 1976 (Folder 24)
  - Grupo Comunista Independiente de Mexico, "The Grupo Comunista Independiente de Mexico and the Fourth International," 1969 (Folder 25)
  - Grupo Comunista Internacionalista (Mexico), statement on Fourth International draft resolution, 1969 (Folder 26)
  - Harding, Ted, "Mass Arrests in Ukraine," 1972 (Folder 27)
  - Harding, Timothy
    - "Election Campaign" (re Brazil), n.d. (Folder 28)
    - "Labor Labor Labor" (re Brazil), n.d. (Folder 29)
  - Hart, Armando, speech, Organizacion Latinoamericana de Solidaridad conference, Havana, 1967 (Folder 30)
  - Hernandez, Ricardo
    - "The Facts on the Split in the Liga Socialista," ca. 1976 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - "Reply to an Essay on Sectarianism," 1976 (Folder 2)
  - Horowitz, Gus, draft reply of Leninist-Trotskyist Faction to International Executive Committee majority of Fourth International, 1973 (Folder 3)
  - Hutter, Trent, "The Tastemakers," 1957 (Folder 4)
  - Jones, Alan, "Marxism and Facts: Healy's Rejection of Dialectical Materialism," 1978 (Folder 5)
  - Jungclas, Georg, "Letter of Sympathy on the Death of Heinrich Brandler to the Arbeiterpolitik Group of Bremen," 1967 (Folder 6)
  - Karsner, Rose, interview by Evelyn Reed, 1960 (Folder 7)
  - Kemp, Tom, "The United States and World Capitalism," 1960 (Folder 8)
  - Konikow, Antoinette, speech on Margaret Sanger, n.d. Authorship uncertain (Folder 9)
  - Lee, Chei, "The First National Convention" (re China), 1954 (Folder 10)
  - Lenheiro, Guilherme, "Regarding the Document on the Soviet Bureaucracy and the Workers States," 1974 (Folder 11)
  - Leninist-Trotskyist Faction (Fourth International)
    - Declaration, 1973. Typescript (Spanish and English) and mimeograph (English) versions with handwritten annotations (Folder 12)
    - "The Key Issues in the Portuguese Revolution," 1975. Typescript (Spanish) and mimeograph (English) versions with handwritten annotations (Folder 13)
    - "Statement on the Portuguese Presidential Elections," 1976 (Folder 14)
  - Liga Comunista (Spain), "Concerning the Draft Resolution on Portugal," 1975. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 15)
  - Liga Socialista (Mexico), "An Alternative in the Elections: Joint PCM-LS Electoral Program," 1975 (Folder 16)
  - Lobaton, Jacqueline de, "The Guillermo Lobaton Case," 1967 (Folder 17)
  - Maglin, Arthur, "Kennedy," 1964 (Folder 18)
  - Maitan, Livio
    - "Draft Resolution of the IEC on China," 1967 (Folder 19)
    - "La Democratie Proletarienne et la Dialectique de la Societe de Transition," 1976 (Folder 20)
  - Mandel, Ernest
    - "Marxism against Eclecticism," 1955 (Folder 21)
    - "The Sino-Soviet Dispute: An Intermediary Balance-Sheet," 1964 (Folder 22)
    - "In Defense of the Vietnamese Revolution," 1966 (Folder 23)
    - "The Cultural Revolution: An Attempt at Interpretation," 1967 (Folder 24)
    - "Sectarianism and Reformism: Apropos the Healy-Lambert Stand on Vietnam," 1968 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - "The Place of the Ninth World Congress in the History of the IVth International," 1969 (Folder 2)
    - "Political Report at the December 1969 Meeting of the International Executive Committee," 1969 (Folder 3)
  - Martin, Jean Paul, "On the Meaning of the 'Dictatorship of the Proletariat, '" 1953 (Folder 4)
  - Mestre, Michele, "The Crisis in the Fourth International: The Required Ideological Rearmament," 1954 (Folder 5)
  - Moreno, Nahuel
    - "Our Party's Break with Pabloism," 1953 (Folder 6)
    - "Report to the Central Committee of the POR Concerning the Letter to the International Secretariat," 1953 (Folder 7)
    - "The Latin American Revolution," ca. 1961 (Folder 8)
    - "The Latin American Situation," ca. 1966 (Folder 9)
    - Un Documento Escandaloso, 1973. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 10-12)
  - Novack, George
    - "Tribute to a Marxist Scholar [John G. Wright]," 1956 (Folder 13)
    - "The Law of Uneven and Combined Development," ca. 1966 (Folder 14)
    - "New Light on Uneven and Combined Development," 1970 (Folder 15)
  - Ochoa, Ricardo, "Continued Harassment of the Political Prisoners in Mexico," 1967 (Folder 16)
  - "On Cannon's Article, 'The I.W.W.': Comments," 1955 (Folder 17)
  - Organizing Committee for Reconstruction of the Fourth International, "Resolution Unanimously Adopted by the Preconference of the International Committee," 1970. Includes accompanying news story from Informations Ouvrieres (Folder 18)
  - Parti Communiste Internationaliste (France)
    - "The August Strikes and Their Significance," 1953 (Folder 19)
    - "Political Notes," No. 1-4, 1953 (Folder 20)
    - "The French Communist Party and the Crisis of Stalinism," ca. 1956 (Folder 21)
  - Parti Suisse du Travail. Lancy Section, statement, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Partido Revolucionario de los Trabajadores (Mexico), "United Front of the Left," 1977 (Folder 2)
  - Partido Socialista de los Trabajadores (Argentina), "Reply," 1974 (Folder 3)
  - Peng, Shu-tse
    - "The October Revolution and Leninism," 1924. Holograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 4)
    - Interviews by David Fender, 1967 (Folder 5)
    - "An Open Letter to the Members of the Chinese Communist Party," 1967 (Folder 6)
    - "The Relationship and Differences between Mao Tse-tung and Liu Shao-chi," 1967 (Folder 7)
    - "Return to the Road of Trotskyism," 1969 (Folder 8)
    - Interview by Dan Styron on Vietnamese Trotskyists, 1973 (Folder 9)
  - Peng, Shu-tse and Ch'en Pi-lan, interview by Herman Kirsch, 1973 (Folder 10)
  - Perry, Hayden, "Los Angeles Hugo Blanco Meeting," 1967 (Folder 11)
  - "Protest by the Old Bolsheviks: A Discussion in the Marx-Engels Institute in Moscow," 1967 (Folder 12)
  - Quijano, Carlos, "Manuitt, Debray, and the Venezuelan Revolution: An Interview with the President of the FLN-FALN," 1967 (Folder 13)
  - Ramirez, Alfonso, et al., "For the Construction and Strengthening of the Latin American Sections of the Fourth International," 1972 (Folder 14)
  - Rangel, Domingo Alberto, interview by Americo Chacon, 1964 (Folder 15)
  - Reed, Evelyn, eulogy for Rose Karsner, 1968 (Folder 16)
  - "Repression of Revolutionary Groups in Chile," 1967 (Folder 17)
  - Reyes, Ezequiel, "Argentina's Political Situation and Its Working Class Crisis of Leadership," 1958 (Folder 18)
  - Roberts, Dick, "Imperialism," 1967 (Folder 19)
  - "Role of the Trotskyists in the Recent Mass Workers Struggles in Spain" (interview of anonymous Spanish Trotskyist), ca. 1975 (Folder 20)
  - Rosdolsky, R., "Joan Robinson's Criticism of Marx," 1963 (Folder 21)
  - Santhal, Jangal, "Naxalbari [India]," 1967 (Folder 22)
  - Socialist Labour League (Great Britain) National Committee, "Trotskyism Betrayed: The SWP Accepts the Political Method of Pabloite Revisionism," 1962. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 23)
  - Socialist Workers Party
    - "Proposed International Resolution as Amended by Cassidy," 1943. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 24)
    - "The Third Chinese Revolution and Its Aftermath," 1955. Typescript and mimeograph versions with handwritten annotations (Folder 25)
  - Socialist Workers Party. National Committee, "The Communes in China," 1959. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 26)
  - Socialist Workers Party. Political Committee
    - "Draft of World Appeal to Orthodox Trotskyists," 1953. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 27)
    - "The Struggle between the Socialist and Capitalist Camps," 1961. Mimeograph (from Socialist Workers Party Discussion Bulletin [1961 May]) with handwritten annotations (Folder 28)
  - Swabeck, Arne, "What Is Behind the New Kremlin Shake-Up?" 1957 (Folder 29)
  - Tate, Ernest, "Healy," 1976 (Folder 30)
  - Thorez, Maurice, interview, 1953 (Folder 31)
  - "The Toronto Meeting of IC Supporters in 1960, " n.d. (Folder 32)
  - Trotskaia, Nataliia Sedova
    - Letter to C. L. R. James, 1940 (Folder 33)
    - "Fabrication of a Trotsky Testament," 1948 (Folder 34)
  - Trotskaia, Nataliia Sedova, and Victor Serge, extract from Vie et Mort de Trotsky, 1951. Printed (French) and typescript (English) versions with handwritten annotations (Folder 35)
  - Trotsky, Leon
    - The Permanent Revolution, 1931. Printed Pioneer Press edition, heavily annotated by hand to indicate corrections for new edition (Folder 36)
    - The History of the Russian Revolution, Volume I, 1932. Printed Simon and Schuster edition with handwritten annotations (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - The History of the Russian Revolution, 1936. Printed three-volume-in-one Simon and Schuster edition with handwritten annotations (Folder 2)
  - Van Heijenoort, Jean, interview by George Weissman, 1976 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - Vereecken, Georges, "On the Hypothesis Advanced by Comrade L. D. Trotsky in the Document 'The USSR in War, '" 1975 (Folder 2)
  - Vitale, Luis
    - "Chile," 1962 (Folder 3)
    - "Towards a Trade Union Center of Latin American Workers," 1962 (Folder 4)
    - "Cuba," 1969 (Folder 5)
  - Voix Ouvriere (Organization: France), "Reconstruct the Fourth International," n.d. (Folder 6)
  - Wang, Fan-hsi, "Memoirs of a Chinese Revolutionary," 1957
    - Chapters 4-7 (Folder 7)
    - Chapters 8-9 (Folder 8)
  - Waters, Mary-Alice, letter to Ernest Mandel, 1979 (Folder 9)
  - Weiss, Myra Tanner, "On Minority Representation," 1954. Mimeograph with handwritten annotations (Folder 10)
  - Williams, Alexander, "Cuba 1966, " 1966 (Folder 11)
  - Williams, B. J., "A New Phase of the Chinese Revolution: Will It Bring a New Upswing of the World Revolution?" 1967 (Folder 12)
  - Wohlforth, Tim
    - "Amendments to PC World Resolution," 1961. Mimeograph (from Socialist Workers Party Discussion Bulletin [1961 June]) with handwritten annotations (Folder 13)
    - "The Postwar Social Overturns and Marxist Theory," 1977 (Folder 14)
  - Wohlforth, Tim, and Nancy Fields, "In Defense of a Revolutionary Perspective," 1975 (Folder 15)
  - Wright, John G., "Feuerbach, Philosopher of Materialism," n.d. (Folder 16)
- REBA HANSEN FILE, 1928-1979.
  Note: Correspondence of Reba Hansen is interfiled with that of Joseph Hansen in CORRESPONDENCE FILE
  - Miscellany, 1938-1957 (Box 67, Folder 17)
  - Speeches and writings, 1928-1979
    - Short stories, ca. 1928-1934. Typescripts (Folder 18)
    - "Trying to Be What I'm Not," ca. 1928-1934. Typescript essay re Joseph Hansen (Folder 19)
    - Notes on Trotsky School course on Karl Marx, Capital, taught by Joseph Hansen, 1953-1954 (Folder 20-22)
    - Letter to the editor, The Militant, re visit to Algeria, ca. 1962. Typescript (Folder 23)
    - Message to Organizacion Latinoamericana de Solidaridad conference, Havana, 1967 June 14. Typescript (Folder 24)
    - Speech, Intercontinental Press anniversary banquet, New York City, 1974 May 5. Typescript (Box 68, Folder 1)
    - "Working with Jim [James P. Cannon]," 1975. Typescript (Folder 2-3)
    - British Broadcasting Corporation televised interview on Leon Trotsky, 1979 October 29. Typed transcript, notes, and contract (Folder 4)
    - Shorthand notes, n.d. (Folder 5)
- BEATRICE HANSEN FILE, 1945-1969
  - Correspondence, 1945-1969
    - General
      - 1945-1967. Includes letters by George Breitman, Oscar Coover, Sr., Duncan Ferguson, Tom Kerry, Ed Shaw, Lawrence Trainor, and Connie Weissman (Box 68, Folder 6)
      - 1968-1969. Includes letters by Jack Barnes, George Breitman, Priscilla Ring, Ed Shaw, Betsey Stone, and Lawrence and Augusta Trainor (Folder 7)
    - Hansen, Allan, 1968-1969 (Folder 8)
    - Hansen, Joseph and Reba, 1962-1969 (Folder 9)
  - Personal documents, 1948-1969. Marriage, divorce and death certificates, address and appointment books, financial records, and trade union and other identification cards (Folder 10-11)
  - Speeches and writings, 1967-1969
    - Eulogy for Rose Karsner, 1968. Typescript (Folder 12)
    - Notes, ca. 1967-1969 (Folder 13)
- LEON TROTSKY FILE, 1903-1979
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1935-1940
    - Cannon, James P., 1937 October 10 (Box 69, Folder 1)
    - Cardenas, Lazaro, 1940 May 31 (Folder 2)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd. (Publishers), 1938 September 25 (Folder 3)
    - Dunayevskaya, Raya, 1939 April 20 (Folder 4)
    - International Communist League. International Secretariat, 1935
      - June 10 (Folder 5)
      - November (Folder 6)
    - Isaacs, Harold R., 1935 August 10 (Folder 7)
    - Lenero, Agustin, 1940 June 9 (Folder 8)
    - Mexico. Procurador de Justicia et al., 1940 May 27 (Folder 9)
    - Mexico. Secretario de Gobernacion et al., 1940 June 13 (Folder 10)
    - El Nacional, 1940
      - June 6 (Folder 11)
      - August (Folder 12)
    - New York Herald-Tribune, 1940 July 27 (Folder 13)
    - New York Public Library, 1940 February 22 (Folder 14)
    - La Prensa, 1940 July 11 (Folder 15)
    - Reyes R., Francisco, 1939 February 11 (Folder 16)
    - Sanchez Salazar, Leandro, 1940
      - May 31 (Folder 17)
      - July 15 (Folder 18)
    - Socialist Workers Party, 1939 January 1 (Folder 19)
    - Workers Party of the U.S., 1935 August 13 (Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Incoming, 1935-1940
    - Abern, Martin, 1935 (Folder 21)
    - Asociacion de Editores de los Estados, 1940 (Folder 22)
    - Excelsior, 1937 (Folder 23)
    - Glotzer, Albert, 1935 (Folder 24)
    - Hoy, 1939 (Folder 25)
    - El Nacional, 1938-1940 (Folder 26)
    - Oehler, Hugo, 1935 (Folder 27)
    - El Tiempo, 1937 (Folder 28)
    - Todo, 1938 (Folder 29)
    - El Universal, 1937 (Folder 30)
  - Speeches and writings, 1903-1940
    - Report to Rossiiskaia Sotsial-demokraticheskaia Rabochaia Partiia 2nd congress, 1903 July. Typescript (in English) (Folder 31)
    - Nashi politicheskiia zadachi, 1904. Mimeograph (in English) (Folder 32)
    - "On the Theses 'Unity and the Youth, '" 1934 December. Typed copy (in English) (Folder 33)
    - Statement on Abraham and Roman Sobolevicius, 1937 February 27. Typescript (in English) (Folder 34)
    - "Concise Answers to Questions Concerning the Spanish Revolution," 1937 September 14. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 35)
    - "On the Sino-Japanese War," 1937 September 23. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 36)
    - "Pacifism and China," 1937 September 23. Mimeograph (in Spanish) (Folder 37)
    - "90 let Kommunisticheskogo manifesta, " 1937 October 30. Mimeograph (in Spanish) (Folder 38)
    - "Kratkie kommentarii k verdiktu," 1937 December 13. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 39)
    - Statement on Vicente Lombardo Toledano, 1938 November 10. Typescript (in English) (Folder 40)
    - "Nationalized Industry and Workers' Management," 1939 May 12. Typescript (in French) (Folder 41)
    - "'Trotskizm' i PSOP," 1939 July 15. Mimeograph (in Spanish) (Folder 42)
    - Note on Walter G. Krivitsky, ca. 1940. Holograph (in Russian) and typescripts (in English and Spanish) (Folder 43)
    - Testament, 1940 February 27. Typed copy (in English) (Folder 44)
    - "Vas obmanyvaiut! Pis'mo v SSSR," 1940 April 23. Printed copy (in Russian) (Folder 45)
    - Statement on Tanaka Memorial, 1940 May 1. Typescript (in English) (Folder 46)
    - "Breves comentarios referentes a las preguntas a David Serrano," 1940 June. Holograph (in Spanish) (Folder 47)
    - "Neobkhodimyi dopolnitel'nyi vopros dlia D. Serrano," 1940 June. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 48)
    - "O Lombardo Toledano" and "O Roberte Sheldone," 1940 June. Typescripts (in Russian and Spanish) (Folder 49)
    - "Voprosy v otnoshenii Davida Serrano," 1940 June. Holograph (in Spanish) and typescript (in Russian) (Folder 50)
    - "El diputado Toledano lanza una nueva calumnia," 1940 June 2. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 51)
    - "Acerca de la respuesta del director de El Nacional, " 1940 June 12. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 52)
    - "Rol' Kremlia v evropeiskoi katastrofe," 1940 June 17. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 53)
    - Statement on Narciso Bassols, 1940 June 25. Typescript (in English) (Folder 54)
    - "Obviniteli ili obviniaemye?" 1940 June 27. Typescript (in Russian) (Folder 55)
    - "Brevas notas sobre la deposicion de la Senorita Belem Estrada," 1940 July. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 56)
    - "Luzhnye podozreniia protiv Roberta Sheldona Kharta," 1940 July 15. Typescript (in Russian) (Folder 57)
    - "Sobre la posible suerte de David Alfaro Siqueiros y otros," 1940 July 23. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 58)
    - "G-nu sud'e," 1940 July 26. Typescript (in Russian) (Folder 59)
    - "Apelacion a la prensa," 1940 July 27. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 60)
    - "El discurso de Molotof," 1940 August 2. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 61)
    - Statement on David Serrano, 1940 August 2. Typescript (in Spanish) (Folder 62)
  - Subject file, 1929-1979
    - General
      - General. Diagram of Coyoacan compound, cipher key, notes, and memoranda, 1938-1953 (Folder 63)
      - Correspondence of Coyoacan household, 1937-1940. Includes letters by Harold R. Isaacs, Felix Morrow, George Novack, Walter O'Rourke, Harold Robins, Max Shachtman, and Jean van Heijenoort. Does not include correspondence of Leon Trotsky (Folder 64)
      - Printed matter. Clippings and printed articles re Leon Trotsky
        - 1937-1959 (Folder 65)
        - 1961-1978 (Folder 66)
      - Hutter, Trent, "Leon Trotsky's Literature and Revolution, " 1957. Typescript (Folder 67)
      - Johnstone, Monty, "The Debate on Socialism in One Country," 1968. Galleys (Folder 68)
      - Retboll, Torben, "Leon Trotsky and the Kronstadt Revolt of March 1921," 1977. Typescript (Folder 69)
      - Robins, Harold, "Recollections," ca. 1950. Typescript (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Archives. Deeds of sale, letters, and memoranda, re disposition and access status of papers of Leon Trotsky, 1935-1977 (Folder 2)
    - Assassination
      - General. Depositions taken by Mexican authorities in connection with investigation of assassination; copies of United States Department of State dispatches re investigation; letter by Esteban Volkov re motion picture film The Assassination of Trotsky; and memoranda, 1940-1978 (Folder 3)
      - Printed matter. Clippings and printed articles
        - 1940-1954 (Folder 4)
        - 1955-1979 (Folder 5)
    - Bibliography, 1953 (Folder 6)
    - Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials. Depositions, memoranda, letters, report, bulletins, and abstract of findings of commission, 1937-1965. Includes depositions by Jan Frankel and Konrad Knudsen, and letters by Charles A. Beard, George Novack and Bernard Wolfe (Folder 7)
    - Government surveillance. Copy of register of United States Department of State and Department of Justice reports, 1929-1941 (Folder 8)
    - Library. List of books and serials in study of Leon Trotsky at time of his death, 1940 (Folder 9)
    - Memorial meetings. Announcements and programs, 1940-1945 (Folder 10)
- NATALIIA SEDOVA TROTSKAIA FILE, 1940-1963
  - Clippings, 1951-1963 (Box 70, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1961
    - Cannon, James P., 1944-1945 (Folder 12)
    - Craipeau, Yvan, 1946 (Folder 13)
    - Distrito Federal (Mexico) Gobernador, 1946 (Folder 14)
    - Novack, George, 1961 (Folder 15)
    - Socialist Workers Party, 1940 (Folder 16)
    - Weber, Jack, 1942 (Folder 17)
    - Wright, John G., 1940 (Folder 18)
  - Financial records, 1941-1961 (Folder 19)
  - Memorial meetings. Announcements, programs, condolence messages, and typescript eulogies by Alfonso Ramirez and Evelyn Reed, 1962 (Folder 20)
  - Speeches and writings, 1940-1961
    - Statement on assassination of Leon Trotsky, ca. 1940. Typescript (Folder 21)
    - Open letter to C. L. R. James, 1940 October 17. Typescripts (Folder 22)
    - Open letter to Parti Communiste Internationaliste (France) (with Benjamin Peret and Grandizo Munis), 1947 June. Mimeograph (Folder 23)
    - Open letter to Fourth International, 1951. Mimeograph (Folder 24)
    - Letter to the editor, New York Post, 1957 April 24. Printed copy (Folder 25)
    - Open letter to Soviet Union. Verkhovnyi Sovet, 1961 November 2. Typescripts (Folder 26)
    - Letter to the editor, France-Soir, 1961 November 9. Printed copy (Folder 27)
    - Will, n.d. Typescript (Folder 28)
- FOURTH INTERNATIONAL FILE, 1930-1980
  - General (material not classifiable under any single country)
    - General
      - Correspondence
        - 1935-1961. Includes letters by James P. Cannon, Farrell Dobbs, Pierre Frank, Albert Glotzer, Albert Goldman, Sam Gordon, Ernest Mandel, George Novack, Michel Pablo, Morris Stein, and Jack Weber (Box 71, Folder 1)
        - 1962. Includes letters by Farrell Dobbs, Ross Dowson, Pierre Frank, Gerry Healy, Livio Maitan, Ernest Mandel, George Novack, Michel Pablo, Art Sharon, and Arne Swabeck (Folder 2)
        - 1963-1968. Includes letters by Jack Barnes, Ross Dowson, Pierre Frank, Sam Gordon, Gerry Healy, Tom Kerry, Ernest and Gisela Mandel, Michel Pablo, Art Sharon, Ed Shaw, Barry Sheppard, and Mary-Alice Waters (Folder 3)
        - 1969. Includes letters by Jack Barnes, Caroline Lund, Livio Maitan, Ernest and Gisela Mandel, and Barry Sheppard (Folder 4)
        - 1970. Includes letters by Jack Barnes, Ross Dowson, Caroline Lund, Livio Maitan, Ernest and Gisela Mandel, Barry Sheppard, and John Steele (Folder 5)
        - 1971-1972. Includes letters by Jack Barnes, Ross Dowson, Gus Horowitz, Livio Maitan, Ernest and Gisela Mandel, John Riddell, and Mary-Alice Waters (Folder 6)